[SPEAKER_02]: So, there's a sutta here called the fāma.
[SPEAKER_02]: Now, on that occasion, the Blessed One was instructing, exhorting, inspiring, gladdening the bhikkhus with a dhamma talk concerning nirvāṇa.
[SPEAKER_02]: Those bhikkhus were listening to the dhamma with eager ears, attending to it as a matter of vital concern, applying their whole minds to it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Then, it occurred to Mara, the evil one.
[SPEAKER_02]: The ascetic Gautama is instructing the bhikkhus.
[SPEAKER_02]: Let me approach the ascetic Gautama in order to confound him.
[SPEAKER_02]: Then, Mara, the evil one, manifested himself in the form of a farmer, carrying a large plough on his shoulder, holding a large goat stick, his hair disheveled, wearing hempen garments, his feet smeared with mud.
[SPEAKER_02]: He approached the Blessed One and said to him,
[SPEAKER_02]: Maybe you've seen oxen, ascetic.
[SPEAKER_01]: What are oxen to you, either one?
[SPEAKER_02]: So then he says, okay, the eye is mine, this is Mara.
[SPEAKER_02]: The eye is mine, ascetic.
[SPEAKER_02]: Forms are mine.
[SPEAKER_02]: Eye contact and its base of consciousness are mine.
[SPEAKER_02]: Where can you go, ascetic, to escape from me?
[SPEAKER_02]: The ear is mine.
[SPEAKER_02]: Ascetic.
[SPEAKER_02]: Sounds are mine.
[SPEAKER_02]: The nose is mine.
[SPEAKER_02]: Tongue is mine.
[SPEAKER_02]: Body is mine.
[SPEAKER_02]: The mind is mine.
[SPEAKER_02]: Ascetic.
[SPEAKER_02]: Mental.
[SPEAKER_02]: The phenomena are mine.
[SPEAKER_02]: Mine contact and its base of consciousness are mine.
[SPEAKER_02]: Where can you go, ascetic, to escape from me?
[SPEAKER_02]: And then the Buddha says, the eye is yours, evil one.
[SPEAKER_02]: Forms are yours.
[SPEAKER_02]: Eye contact and its base of consciousness are yours.
[SPEAKER_02]: But, evil one, where there is no eye, no forms, no eye contact and its base of consciousness, there is no place for you there, evil one.
[SPEAKER_02]: The ear is yours.
[SPEAKER_02]: The nose is yours.
[SPEAKER_02]: The tongue is yours.
[SPEAKER_02]: The body is yours.
[SPEAKER_02]: Mind is yours, evil one.
[SPEAKER_02]: Phenomena are yours.
[SPEAKER_02]: Mind contact and its base of consciousness are yours.
[SPEAKER_02]: But, evil one, where there is no mind, no phenomena, no mind contact and its base of consciousness, there is no place for you there, evil one.
[SPEAKER_02]: Then there's a verse, Mara says, that of which they say it's mine,
[SPEAKER_02]: And, and those who speak in terms of mine, if your mind exists among these, you won't escape me, ascetic.
[SPEAKER_02]: And the Buddha says, that which they speak of is not mine.
[SPEAKER_02]: I'm not one of those who speak of mine.
[SPEAKER_02]: You should know thus, oh evil one, even my path you will not see.
[SPEAKER_02]: Then Mara, the evil one, disappeared right there.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it quite clearly illustrates where the problem is.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the problem is not in the eye, in the sights, in the consciousness established upon it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not even in the pressure that eye exhibits, the sights exhibit on you, the contact, usually translated as contact, but it's really like a pressure.
[SPEAKER_02]: None of those is a problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: Problem is regarding it as mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Problem is having
[SPEAKER_01]: The assumption of ownership in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And on many other occasions, that's what was said.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's because you take that which belongs to Mārā, Mārā does with you what he pleases.
[SPEAKER_01]: What is it that belongs to Mārā?
[SPEAKER_01]: I belongs to Mārā, sights belong to Mārā, I consciousness belong to Mārā, nose and so on, everything else.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, how do you then escape Mārā?
[SPEAKER_01]: How do you then escape suffering?
[SPEAKER_01]: Without destroying eyes, sights, sounds, smells, tastes, touches.
[SPEAKER_01]: Without avoiding contact.
[SPEAKER_01]: Without giving in to pressure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Without trying to deny pressure.
[SPEAKER_02]: By not taking ownership of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And how would that be done?
[SPEAKER_01]: How would you not take the ownership?
[SPEAKER_02]: Because, not taking ownership,
[SPEAKER_01]: You can own that.
[SPEAKER_01]: The attitude of nothing is mine.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: But if you see, like the Buddha's saying here, the I is yours.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, if you see that that which everything kind of depends on, isn't mine.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, just seeing that I's cannot be yours.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sights cannot be yours.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the only way to see that correctly, is to see that they cannot be yours, through your current mistake in ownership.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the important point.
[SPEAKER_01]: Crucial point.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's the crucial point.
[SPEAKER_01]: You need to see... Because, see, you read that sutra and the Buddha said, I'm not the one who says mine, I don't use mine.
[SPEAKER_01]: And people say, ah, so I must stop saying mine.
[SPEAKER_01]: As if, just by not saying mine, you somehow transcend
[SPEAKER_01]: So, although it's a mistake, it's real as such.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, first, you have to accept that ownership is there.
[SPEAKER_01]: You regard your senses as yours.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sites that please you, sites that displease you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Basically, you regard your body, the basis of your body, the basis of your experience, as belonging to you.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, within that ownership, you then need to discern that these things are actually impossible to own.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not in response to your ownership.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, oh, ownership is a problem, so I will go around and keep telling myself that I can't own these things even if I want to, but the only reason you're doing that, or rather the reason you're doing that, is rooted in you trying to basically get rid of the ownership, and you own that, because you're acting out of the same ownership.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're affirming it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're craving for it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Craving against it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Craving is there.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, accepting that there is ownership, and it's not a matter of choice, because as long as there is eyes, there is ownership.
[SPEAKER_01]: As long as there are sights, there is ownership of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, allowing that ownership to endure, but to see that it's dependent on something... Once you become skilled, so to speak, in not denying ownership, not acting blindly out of it,
[SPEAKER_01]: But, eh... seeing it for what it is, practicing restraint in regard to it, sure, but allowing it to endure, then you can get to see what's within that ownership, which is the basis, necessary basis for that ownership, which cannot be owned.
[SPEAKER_02]: The basis for that ownership.
[SPEAKER_02]: What makes that ownership possible in the first place?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what is a necessary condition for the ownership of eyes and sights?
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, things that please me.
[SPEAKER_01]: I want to go and look at something agreeable.
[SPEAKER_01]: What is a necessary basis for that experience?
[SPEAKER_01]: The body.
[SPEAKER_01]: The body, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or, more specifically, the eyes and things to be looked at.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, say, in half an hour, you want to go and, I don't know, watch a parade.
[SPEAKER_01]: You see a movie, whatever it is, something you want visually pleasing for you.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you have the prospect of engaging with sights.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you set, you know, you accept it, you know, you get ready and you start going wherever that is happening.
[SPEAKER_01]: But...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you're already committed to that.
[SPEAKER_01]: And from the point of, like, even before when you just decide to do it,
[SPEAKER_01]: To engage with the sights.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is a necessary basis.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's a prospect of those sights, possibility.
[SPEAKER_01]: They need to be there, to some extent.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or at least, there is a likelihood of them being there.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, your entire project of planning to engage, making effort to engage with with the sense object, is fully within necessary basis of those things.
[SPEAKER_01]: Necessary container, necessary dependence upon those things.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, you go there and, turns out, the movie is cancelled.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yet, this whole time, you were acting as if it were there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Failing to see that the necessary basis, doesn't matter how much you're in control, how many... like you can afford a ticket, you have... you can get there in time, you book your space, everything, all of these things you can control, are fully within the necessary base of things that fundamentally cannot be controlled.
[SPEAKER_01]: Such as things get cancelled, things get destroyed.
[SPEAKER_01]: You die on the way up there.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that might not be obvious to some, that the... it's not just sight... sights that have the eye as a necessary basis, but any possible... any possibility... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, on the level, that's where everything starts, basically, and stays, and maintains itself within the mind, enduring.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when you have the prospect of going to see the movie, there is no movie present here.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just a thought.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you're not seeing any of that.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that thought stands for what your eyes are at the time.
[SPEAKER_01]: As in, that's why all the senses, the five senses, meet in the mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's where they're discerned.
[SPEAKER_02]: And it may even be something that's not attended to, like, consciously attended to.
[SPEAKER_02]: You know, like, people make decisions.
[SPEAKER_02]: And you don't need to sort of analyze it.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, you just... Whatever you're about to do, you see it as an arisen prospect that endures.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you can then exercise either restraint or giving into it.
[SPEAKER_01]: If it's wholesome, you can do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: If it's unwholesome, if it's rooted in desire, if it's rooted in distraction, you restrain yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Either way, prospects will be in your mind for doing this or doing that.
[SPEAKER_01]: You cannot not do anything.
[SPEAKER_01]: You say, I'm not doing anything that you're doing.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, once you have sort of eradicated engagement, careless engagement with prospects that are rooted in desire, then the ones that you can do, you then get to understand how, like, basically the threshold where your commitment sort of overreaches, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, I need to do this.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's fine.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't necessarily need to be emotionally invested in doing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, if things change before you've completed it, before you've done it the way you wanted it, or
[SPEAKER_01]: Whichever way it goes, you won't be emotionally affected.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you never lost the perspective that doesn't matter what you do, it's fundamentally rooted, contained within the basis, within the container that cannot be owned.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the only way to arrive at true non-ownership of things is through ownership.
[SPEAKER_01]: Through learning how to accept the ownership and allow it to endure and not blindly act towards it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or trying to get rid of it, if it displeases you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that's another thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: When you have a disagreeable experience affects you, that's why you're affected.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it's yours.
[SPEAKER_01]: You want to get rid of the owning unpleasant things.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, I own this.
[SPEAKER_01]: This is mine.
[SPEAKER_01]: But look, it's turning really bad.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, I'll get rid of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: I will stop owning it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what it would have meant in brief.
[SPEAKER_01]: Suffering is being united with what we don't want and separated from things we want.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, owning things you don't want and not owning things you want.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the root of every suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: What you want and what you don't want.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why, like, the sense restraint needs to come first, because ownership is there, which means you're already acting out of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you need to stop acting out of it, in a sense, that would perpetuate that desire and anything unwholesome that's rooted in it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It still won't free you from the ownership, but it will certainly set up things to be understood, as in understanding ownership in that sense that you're not emotionally invested in it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's the true ownership, true lack of ownership.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not like throwing away things you own, destroying them, because then, if that were the case, you would say you just have to pull your eyes out, and you're free from ownership of sights.
[SPEAKER_01]: The true ownership is not being pressured by those things, not owning the contact of them, not being contacted by them.
[SPEAKER_02]: Mara says, that of which they say it's mine, and those who speak in terms of mine, if your mind exists among these, you would escape me.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if there is absolutely no feeling pressuring you, manifesting, arising, whatever, making you act on account of what's there in your experience, whether wanted or not wanted, you're not owning it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's always... also you can use that as a criteria of, oh, well, am I attached to this?
[SPEAKER_01]: If it were to change, if it were to become otherwise, if it were to be taken away, would I experience this agreeable feeling that would then overwhelm my mind?
[SPEAKER_01]: Would I basically suffer on account of it?
[SPEAKER_01]: If you're not sure, means yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if doubt, means yes, you will suffer on account of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you have to be absolutely clear that... and that's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you can... you don't need to go and lose these things or you don't need to go and watch a movie to know that you're doing it out of desire.
[SPEAKER_01]: You already know it when the prospect has arisen on the level of possibility.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't need to go to see that the movie is cancelled or not.
[SPEAKER_01]: The fact is you're acting out of the desire.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, even if you don't get to see the movie, you still acted out of the desire on the level of your thought.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if the thing got cancelled and you didn't actually engage to the extent you wanted to engage, you still engage with the desire.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because desire is not in those things, it's on the level of your mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, same, then, you can imagine things that are dear to you or things that are threatening to you.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't need to go and engage with them.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just think about it and you're already either affected or not.
[SPEAKER_01]: Either craving to be free from it, either craving against it or craving for more of it.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's like the sutta where they're in Jeta's wood in Samādhi and the Buddha says, would you be upset if someone came along and took away all those branches and twigs and leaves and things and said no?
[SPEAKER_02]: Because why?
[SPEAKER_02]: Because they're not ours.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, because you don't care about them.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: You absolutely have no emotional interest in random twigs.
[SPEAKER_01]: He says, well, that's how you should regard your body.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Your eyes and everything else.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, as I said, it's certainly in the... in the beginning of that practice, the attitude will never... like, you know, somebody comes and reads the sutra, then immediately you think, okay, so ownership is bad.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, yeah, ownership is the root of suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: So then, whatever you do, you will... well, in the beginning, you won't be able to see that whatever you do will be on account of trying to get rid of the ownership.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the only way to get rid of the ownership is to accept it and understand it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't understand it if you keep trying to get rid of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, it's not self, it's not self.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's an atta, it's an atta.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or, oh, look, look, look, that's attachment.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just throw things away.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just get rid of stuff.
[SPEAKER_01]: Get rid of stuff.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you are not understanding ownership, because whenever you face it, you're just turning away, trying to deny it, get rid of it, get rid of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Isn't it like trying to treat a matter as a denial, so you can...
[SPEAKER_01]: And provide an explanation for it.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're not... they're not... they don't belong to you anyway, so that's... that's okay.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the whole, you know, sexual intercourse is okay, because I'm not a... it's not me, it's just the body, it's animal instincts, that I'm an animal, a human animal.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's... that's even more dishonest, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, yeah, I know, I know.
[SPEAKER_01]: But what I'm saying, like, you... you... you must have abandoned that attitude through your behavior.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even before you can become aware of the ownership on its own terms.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that's the point.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, people can read and declare themselves Buddhist and then just say that nothing is real anyway, nothing belongs to me, I can do whatever I want.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Only if you're an arahant, the statement, nothing belongs to me, is true.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, are you an arahant?
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus, you saying everything is an atta, is false.
[SPEAKER_01]: From your experience, it's a lie.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, or wishful thinking.
[SPEAKER_01]: Wishful thinking, sure, sure.
[SPEAKER_02]: Based on the assumption that if I keep telling myself this, I'll be fine.
[SPEAKER_01]: That, for me, it's very dishonest.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you're lying to yourself by doing that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Same way, oh, I can do these things without attachment.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, don't do them.
[SPEAKER_01]: Don't do them at all.
[SPEAKER_01]: If there is no attachment, there is no pressure.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's another... that's another sutra where the Buddha said...
[SPEAKER_01]: Sometimes I ask monks to... to abandon some little trifle thing, something not so important, but it's still kind of an obstacle.
[SPEAKER_01]: So the Buddha would ask them to... to get... stop doing that.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then some monk said, well, look, this is nothing.
[SPEAKER_01]: I can stop this whenever I want.
[SPEAKER_01]: And because of that, he doesn't stop it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And he gets fettered by it, because he didn't stop it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Stopping it, doesn't matter what you think about it, stopping it will free you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not stopping it won't free you.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you think you can stop it anytime, and it's true, you can stop it anytime, and because of that thought, you don't stop it at any time.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, another monk says, oh, this is trifle, this is little, this is insignificant.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, he makes the effort and he stops it.
[SPEAKER_01]: He's free from it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And in the simile, he said that the first monk, the one who doesn't stop it, is like a qu
[SPEAKER_01]: Who is sort of tethered by the rotten ropes and tiny little strings, but the quail is weak, and that's more than enough to keep it high.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the other one is like an elephant that gets tied by leather straps, but he still breaks them.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's often when people say, I can stop this whenever I want.
[SPEAKER_01]: But what you can't want is to stop it whenever you want.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't want to want to stop it.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you were to want to stop it, you could stop it whenever you want, but you can't want to stop it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why you end up not stopping it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yeah, like, when people say, oh, you can have sexual intercourse without being attached, that's ridiculous.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, not just as Buddha said millions of times, that's impossible in the suttas, but also, like, how can you even engage to any extent of, like, physical pursuit of sensuality without being pressurized, without accepting it, without acting out of it, without... and that's already...
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what I'm saying.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, even before you go and get to see the movie or see that the movie is cancelled, you've already engaged with sensual aspect of it by deciding to do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's on the level of the thought.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's already central perception.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, central perception doesn't matter if it's the actual movie or of the thought of the possibility of the movie.
[SPEAKER_01]: Perception of the visual domain, which is both actual and possible, is there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Basically, it's an image.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's an image, sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: On account of which, you've been pressured.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you already accepted the desire on the level of your thought, and that thought remains enduring.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the whole point.
[SPEAKER_01]: If, say, your desire of... the thought of your desire, you accept it, and then it disappears, you wouldn't know where to go, what to do.
[SPEAKER_01]: You wouldn't have context for your action of seeking such and such movie, or entertainment, or group of people, or fun.
[SPEAKER_01]: That desire remains.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that desire makes every further engagement within it to be within that desire.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that's why you can't necessarily judge things externally, whether this is always desire, this is not always desire.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sexually, because it's always desire.
[SPEAKER_01]: Killing, it's always desire.
[SPEAKER_01]: Things that basically are clearly against the precepts are always rooted in desire.
[SPEAKER_01]: But there are sometimes things that are root... can be rooted in desire internally, but not always.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sometimes they're not necessarily rooted in desire.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you were to only judge things externally, it means there's always desire.
[SPEAKER_01]: Look, he has these possessions, he's always attached to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Look, he's eating, he's always craving for his food.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you can actually not accept desire on the level of the thought, and then even if you eat, none of those actions that follow would... well, now they would be within non-acceptance of desire.
[SPEAKER_01]: And even if you practice restraint, if you accept desire on the level of thought, and then restrain yourself physically or verbally, you're still within the desire.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that's where desire is rooted.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's on the level of accepting those possibilities, those images in your mind, like, I want that, I don't want that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Your restraint is determined by your desire.
[SPEAKER_02]: What do you mean, sorry?
[SPEAKER_02]: You mean, so even if you're restraining yourself,
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, like, restraint is necessary and good, but yeah, it will still be within the desire.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, when the mind is uprooted from that desire, or rather, desire is uprooted from the mind, then, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, even if you're like, look, look all the nice food he's eating.
[SPEAKER_01]: That doesn't mean he's attached.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's what the Buddha said himself.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sometimes he gets those, you know, queens and kings serving with their own hands the finest possible food, and there's absolutely no desire in his mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: He would sometimes eat a bowl full to the brim, sometimes two bowls full to the brim.
[SPEAKER_01]: If he's hungry, there is a practical need for such amount of food.
[SPEAKER_01]: If he walked for 30 kilometers across Bihar or something.
[SPEAKER_01]: And there is absolutely no attachment.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you judge the food, the attachment by the amount of food you eat, then you wouldn't respect the Buddha.
[SPEAKER_02]: There's a whole sutta about it.
[SPEAKER_01]: When that man was praising him, he said, oh, his disciples eat little and he eats little.
[SPEAKER_01]: He said, no, I have disciples who don't eat for days.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I would sit and the Queen would serve me herself, like to the brim, full bowl of whatever you can possibly imagine.
[SPEAKER_01]: If they were to respect me because of that, they wouldn't.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the same with the lodgings and the medicines and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the root of the desire is in the root of ownership, which is on the level of your mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: See, if you were like, say, practicing or maintaining, recollecting the context of death,
[SPEAKER_01]: When you have a thought of going to watch a movie, and in the back of your mind, you refuse to abandon the context that you might die within the next out-breath.
[SPEAKER_01]: Would any central pool, movie, company, other people, would any of that would be able to make it worthwhile, if you think that you might die next second?
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: How can you possibly accept further down the line things that depend upon your life, when your life is up?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why that is, like, if you maintain that kind of perspective, that kind of recollectedness, sati of death, you will abandon centrality, the very least.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, let's say, engaging with a film, watching a film, it implies... Well, think of it like this.
[SPEAKER_01]: Think of it practically.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't think you're going to die, and you want to watch a film, and you enjoy it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a funny, good movie, but... Now...
[SPEAKER_01]: Just before the movie, somebody tells you, I got your doctor's results.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you have 24 hours, maybe, at most.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Would you go and watch the same movie and spend three hours watching it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Or even just, you got six months to do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sure, sure, sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even six months.
[SPEAKER_01]: When somebody reorders the importance of the context for you, would you then engage with the movie?
[SPEAKER_01]: You would have no desire for it either.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the necessary basis for your desire is lack of context.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You think you can own the eyes.
[SPEAKER_01]: You think you own the eyes.
[SPEAKER_01]: You are the owner of the eyes.
[SPEAKER_01]: You took that for granted.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus, now, let me find things that will engage my eyes presently.
[SPEAKER_01]: But somebody comes and tells you you were going to lose... you're going to lose everything, not just your eyes.
[SPEAKER_01]: How can you possibly then care for random sights, sounds, smells, tastes, touches?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you don't want to wait for that to happen, because if you haven't practiced beforehand, it would be too late for you to make effort.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you want to start basically regaining, reclarifying, recollecting this perspective that is there.
[SPEAKER_01]: You are truly like... the movie can be cancelled or not.
[SPEAKER_01]: But one thing for sure, you cannot avoid dying.
[SPEAKER_02]: But that's the thing, your enjoyment of the film requires a kind of...
[SPEAKER_02]: What's happening next?
[SPEAKER_01]: You're always...
[SPEAKER_01]: It requires life to be there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: It requires a kind of...
[SPEAKER_02]: I'm going to find out what's... Well, that's what it means.
[SPEAKER_01]: The sights need eyes.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if there is no persistence of functioning eyes, sights are meaningless.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's where life is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Persistence of senses.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're living senses.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm alive.
[SPEAKER_01]: Senses are mine, thus this life is mine.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm in control of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, all you need to do is stop ignoring the fact that you already know.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, that's why, like, people, if you say something, oh, be careful, like, oh, no, no, don't say that, don't say that, like, phew!
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, now you're gonna, you know, bad luck, because you said that you might go blind or something.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, but you might go blind.
[SPEAKER_01]: You might get sick.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, but you must not say it, because it makes me afraid and fills me with anxiety.
[SPEAKER_01]: How could that be possible if you're not truly liable to it?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it really
[SPEAKER_01]: Fear and anxiety are the reminders of that which you are liable to.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when I say, oh, please don't make me scared about, you know, that I'll die or go blind and lose my senses, means just don't remind me of what I already know, what I am subject to.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's the that's the core of the Buddhist practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: Stop ignoring that, by any means necessary.
[SPEAKER_01]: The divine messengers, again, it's not like some poetic inspiration of how everybody will die.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, it's recognizing that it doesn't matter what you do, to what extent, for how long.
[SPEAKER_01]: How many times?
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: You are live.
[SPEAKER_01]: You are, at any time, subject to death, subject to change, subject to loss.
[SPEAKER_01]: Basically, at any time, you're not in control of your own basis, of your own experience.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's right.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, firstly, recognize... that was the first step, recognizing that you're subject to birth, subject to sickness.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the first step, and that's the step within which every other step is contained.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, there was that sutra on the search.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why am I, who is subject to death,
[SPEAKER_02]: I'm searching for something that is also subject to death.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I've got all this death, subject to deathness, with me.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, now I must go and search for other things that are also death.
[SPEAKER_00]: I've already fulfilled death.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you're saying, like, you recognize that you are subject to loss.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're subject to death, actually.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, you don't really... Like, people, what you just described, that's not understanding you're subject to death.
[SPEAKER_01]: People might say, yeah, I'm subject to death.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, you see what you're going to do next.
[SPEAKER_01]: If your next move is within something that's also subject to death, it means you're using that to basically distract yourself from the fact that you're subject to death.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you're not really staying on the level of, I am subject to death, because if you are, you would genuinely lose the desire for any further engagement down the line of death.
[SPEAKER_01]: It would be inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, am I...
[SPEAKER_01]: Am I fully turned away from these things that are further within death?
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: It means I haven't fully understood what being subject to death means.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sorry.
[SPEAKER_00]: But as the Buddha was saying, you know... That's what the sense of urgency... Yeah, why am I... why must I go and seek that which is also subject to death?
[SPEAKER_01]: Also subject to... And that becomes apparent when you truly feel that sense of urgency that you're subject to death.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, well, I feel this.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's way too...
[SPEAKER_01]: Threatening, too unpleasant, too serious to ignore.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, how can then I possibly go in search for other things that are within that depth?
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's not on the level of just reason it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't just reason it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or rather, people can reason it, which means it's going to be rooted in you trying to avoid it, or you covering up the perspective through your reasoning of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, practically speaking, it would be impossible to engage with sense objects,
[SPEAKER_01]: If you're within the context of death, it's impossible.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then you reverse that and have a look.
[SPEAKER_01]: Am I engaging or not?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Means, I cannot then at the same time think that I am established upon the the context of death.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because I am engaging, I am still wanting these things.
[SPEAKER_01]: As I said, literally, so, if you have 24 hours or even less left to live,
[SPEAKER_01]: And there is possible way out from that perilous situation that awaits for you.
[SPEAKER_01]: What would you choose?
[SPEAKER_01]: Finding the way out of death?
[SPEAKER_01]: Or, oh, let me go and watch this movie and, like, make the most of my time that's left?
[SPEAKER_01]: It's, it's, it's, the choice is automatic.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why the Guru would always say, for whoever, and literally, it doesn't matter if it's a patujan or an arahant,
[SPEAKER_01]: Whenever you do something, whenever you want something, you do it because it's deep down inside, it is rooted in your notion of my own well-being.
[SPEAKER_01]: Always.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's... you engage with desire because desire is unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, through engagement with it, you try to get rid of the pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: Your engagement in pursuit of arahantship, because you understood that underneath it all, again, it's all... it's... it's... you're subjected to pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, your own well-being is basically overcoming pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just... by what means you do it, it's going to make you bound to pain or free from pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when it comes to such a clear-cut choice, death waits for you, possible escape or ignoring it.
[SPEAKER_01]: The choice is automatic.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because the only reason you've been ignoring it before is because that was the closest to your means of escape.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's quite a thought to have, if you weren't told before that.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm subject to death, but then the Buddha said, the thought process is, why don't I seek that which is deathless, which is not subject to death?
[SPEAKER_01]: Why don't I seek the way out of death?
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, who has that thought?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, the person that has developed the context of death would.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I think, back in the day, people were much less dishonest with themselves.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, more of them would have had that, upon hearing the Buddha.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, you need to unclutter your life seriously, mentally, in order just to gain the perspective of what you are subjected to, either way.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, you get a sense of the escape from it.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, if you properly understand that I'm subject to death,
[SPEAKER_02]: You wouldn't be searching for...
[SPEAKER_02]: It would be inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_02]: ...something that is also subject to that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, it would be inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you even know, you can get a hint of that, you know, like when you get sick because you were careless, you were eating, you know, crap food or whatever else, and then there's a bit of a scare,
[SPEAKER_01]: You're ill now, you've been ill for a week, you couldn't get out of the bed, food poisoning, and you're like, oh, I'll never do that again.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because now, you know, the stakes are high, you feel it, the anxiety is there, a sense of urgency.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then you recover, and completely, that context of that urgency of, I'll be careful next, is gone.
[SPEAKER_01]: And there you go, you're doing it again.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because the mind is so fickle.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the mind is fickle because you keep it so.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you, you, you basically, eh...
[SPEAKER_02]: You're not rooting it in.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're not training it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're not training against it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're just giving in to it, and that's... it's going to bring to its increase.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're cultivating weakness.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's all like... like... it's... it's...
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't matter if you're an absolute beginner, or if you've been practicing for, whatever, decades.
[SPEAKER_01]: Reading the suttas and so on, that is the context that remains unchanged.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that you should remain clarifying, and dwelling in, and maintaining, or protecting it, if you've developed it properly.
[SPEAKER_01]: What you're subjected to it, actually.
[SPEAKER_01]: And... because death means impossible to own.
[SPEAKER_01]: Death means lack of ownership, utterly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Death means things that I own, are actually rooted in that which I can't own.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, even if you're just just starting about Buddhism, that's your practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: Keep the precepts that will basically train you in strength of restraint.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if you don't, and then you start thinking about this death and stuff, well, you might be flying left and right, in terms of things you decide to do, or outrun.
[SPEAKER_01]: But now you've said no to that type of engagement with sense objects.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you start clarifying what you are subjected to.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, you will be able to withstand anxiety, sense of urgency, all these things, without, like, panicking and giving in to ridiculous actions of even madness, and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, it's not optional.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's no other way than the way of the divine messengers that the Buddha described.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just whether you're going to equip yourself to be able to withstand their way, or not.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why the Buddha said, sometimes someone's progress is painful,
[SPEAKER_01]: Someone else's isn't.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's the same way.
[SPEAKER_01]: It has to be the same way.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whether you're going to suffer on account of it or not, is whether you can take it or not.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, even if somebody is not interested in the complete freedom from suffering and arahantship,
[SPEAKER_01]: A layman, but still values the Buddha's teaching, that's your practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: Keep the precepts and whatever you engage from the moment you wake up, the moment you go to sleep, try and have it against the backdrop of, I am subject to death.
[SPEAKER_01]: I might not live the next day.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, everything will be... well, it will even out.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even as a lay person who still engages with family, centrality, duties, distraction, it will significantly even out.
[SPEAKER_01]: Your desires, your passions will even out.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you do... you refuse to, like, give in completely.
[SPEAKER_01]: You keep at least one percent of your decision to engage, have it against the fundamental context that, fundamentally, things will be taken away.
[SPEAKER_01]: Cannot be mined.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's basically beginning of wisdom, even for a householder.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you could see how different that is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, actively thinking the thoughts of the context that you're subjected to, as opposed to having your practice of just mindlessly watching your nostrils for an hour a day, and then go about carelessly giving in to desire and everything else, because you've done your duty.
[SPEAKER_02]: No, you don't have to watch your nostrils at all.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't need to meditate at all.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because this will be the meditation, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: Instead of, this is when I do it, it's done all the time.
[SPEAKER_01]: Literally, putting things in the right perspective.
[SPEAKER_01]: How can you put something in perspective, if you have no perspective?
[SPEAKER_01]: How can you gain perspective, unless you start investigating where the perspective is?
[SPEAKER_01]: And same, like, if you're a monk and committed a whole life to this practice, same.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whatever you're about to do, whatever you're doing against the book, you might not live through this.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's a valid thought.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a valid context.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, could you say then, say a lay person's meditation could be just
[SPEAKER_02]: Rather than staring at the nostrils for half an hour...
[SPEAKER_01]: Reflection.
[SPEAKER_01]: ...thinking about clarifying the death.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is a samādhi without sati.
[SPEAKER_01]: And sati, as we said, it's recollecting the right context.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's your samādhi.
[SPEAKER_01]: When that context, it becomes less changeable or harder to lose, you can say you have samādhi.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yeah, absolutely.
[SPEAKER_01]: Your practice of samādhi and concentration should be practice of recollecting the right context.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is?
[SPEAKER_01]: Context of death, context of aging, context of sickness, context that it's impossible to own the eye organ, it's impossible to own the nose organ, and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, if I cannot own these eyes, then how can any sight sound, any sights that come through it, or any sounds, how can that possibly be mine?
[SPEAKER_01]: When, like, sights are inconceivable without the necessary basis of eyes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Functioning eyes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Think about that, feel it, sense of urgency, allow it to endure, and restraint will become effortless.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or, certainly, it will require less effort.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you realize, by not engaging, I'm not exposing myself to risk of death, of losing, of being.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what Buddha compared going down the path of sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like climbing up the tree to eat the mangoes at the top.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, exposing yourself to the risk of falling down, somebody chopping the tree.
[SPEAKER_01]: Millions of reasons can happen to that tree.
[SPEAKER_01]: Unless you come down, you will suffer on account of that.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you come down, doesn't matter if somebody cuts the trees.
[SPEAKER_01]: Doesn't matter if somebody burned the whole cinema down.
[SPEAKER_01]: I lost desire in watching movies there.
[SPEAKER_01]: It will not affect me.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have that backdrop.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, mindfulness, as in recollectedness of the backdrop, the right backdrop, the right context, and samādhi is maintaining it and protecting it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that would result in fully understanding it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, mindfulness, that was obviously the result of your of your restraint, not engaging by default.
[SPEAKER_01]: Default have a watch a movie, I watch a movie.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sense restraint.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, sīla,
[SPEAKER_01]: Through that mindfulness, bring samādhi.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just fully establish this.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, the context remains enduring, despite what's happening around you.
[SPEAKER_01]: The context doesn't need to change.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the whole point.
[SPEAKER_01]: You only need to protect it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Basically, you protect it from yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: You protect the context from you abandoning the context.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, once you stop doing things that would interfere with the context, that's how you protect it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the natural result of that is fully understanding of that context and fully understanding of things what you used to do and how you used to do them in order to basically avoid facing the context.
[SPEAKER_00]: When that context is always there, steady, composed, samādhi, then you can't dictate your actions, your decisions in the future.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then you don't need to do an action.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, and now I will not go and engage with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Non-engagement will be automatic.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, sīla brings samādhi, brings pañña.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's how it works.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, that's the... And either way, sati is there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Recollectedness of the context is there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Necessary for sīla, necessary for samādhi, necessary for pañña.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, whatever happens in life, something comes up, but there's a building possibility for a building project.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you've got the backdrop of, I'm going to die...
[SPEAKER_01]: I might not live for tomorrow, let alone a ten-year project.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know how far you're going to be engaged in that project.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or you can engage, and literally, like, on a daily basis, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't need to make that decision that every day I will re-evaluate and re-engage with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just make a decision to not lose the context that you might not live through.
[SPEAKER_01]: Means, whenever you end up being engaged, it's going to be at the arm's length.
[SPEAKER_00]: You'll be doing that which is actually practically important.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Rather than passionately... Passionate, blind, sort of self-fueling ambition.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: That will become inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, there's a sutta that says, develop... the Buddha says, develop composure, develop samādhi, bhikkhus, because a bhikkhu with samādhi developed, sees things as they really are.
[SPEAKER_02]: What does he see as they really are?
[SPEAKER_02]: I can't remember if it's the aggregates or the senses, but... Sure.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because they are already like that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, but you're now... the context is now firmly established.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not having the right context means having the wrong context.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: There's nothing in between.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means the wrong context will be obscuring how things are.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's exactly what the Māra says.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, like, no, this is yours.
[SPEAKER_01]: This is mine.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the mind is there.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're affected by it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why the Māra controls you.
[SPEAKER_01]: And Māra himself cannot see anything other than ownership.
[SPEAKER_02]: Which is why...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, through Mara's ownership, through Mara's domain, you understand the nature of that domain, and that's how you stop owning it.
[SPEAKER_01]: The Buddha says, even my path you will not see.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't mean how I used to be.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Always.
[SPEAKER_01]: Past is understood against the same backdrop.
[SPEAKER_01]: Future is understood.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why there is no more wandering about in saṃsara.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you understood the aggregates.
[SPEAKER_01]: You understood the framework that is impossible to own.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's what we said before.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't lose what you recollected, accidentally.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you recollected the context of death correctly, you don't need to say, okay, I'm gonna die, I'm gonna die.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: You recollected it's there.
[SPEAKER_01]: All you need to do is keep a corner of your eye on what you're about to do next.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not what you're doing, but what you're planning to do.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're always planning something to do.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's always implicit.
[SPEAKER_01]: Possibility of extending what I'm doing now, whatever, has to be there.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what you keep an eye on.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's how you protect that that doorway.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, so I am subject to death.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what am I doing?
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm sitting here.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, now I'm giving in to such and such thoughts of sensual nature or nature of ill will.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, you can only do that by choosing to do it, which means then choosing to turn away from the context of death.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you don't make the choice to turn away from it, that's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: The context of you being subjected to death is still there.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you protect it.
[SPEAKER_01]: By not intentionally throwing it away.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the clearer that becomes, the easier to protect it becomes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because now you think that all these things are happening random to me, and these random things can take away my mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whenever mindfulness is taken away, means there has been setting in of desire, aversion or distraction.
[SPEAKER_01]: And those things cannot not be intentional.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sorry.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're always intentional.
[SPEAKER_01]: You cannot accidentally engage with sensual desire.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's on the level of the thought that you've said yes to.
[SPEAKER_01]: You cannot accidentally perform an act of ill-will, or accidentally distract yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's always rooted in you choosing to do so.
[SPEAKER_01]: You stop choosing to do so, you cannot possibly obscure the context then.